attention we my application to oist has
gotten me an interview
at the end of may i'll talk to some
professors in okinawa on zoom
so for this week's video i'm gonna
practice my pitch
a few weeks ago my talking squid video
essay was about fristen's
free energy principle neuroscience's
latest model of the sentient being
i described a project involving bees i i
still like the idea
but it's another classic example of me
getting way
too complicated way too quick the
project i
actually proposed to oist is much more
simple
carl fristen demonstrated his free
energy principle by training a program
to navigate a maze
i want to train two programs to navigate
a maze
one predator and one prey the predator
wants to minimize its distance to the
prey the prey
wants to maximize its distance from the
predator
at hoist i'd like to make this work
continuously
but for now let's leave it discreet like
a board game
in each time step the predator and prey
both
move one space up left down or right
the two agents compete learning how to
best
interpret their perceptions of reality
by minimizing
free energy in a generative adversarial
network
last time i talked about free energy i
skipped most of the deeper math
now i've read and reread enough
tutorials to go over one step by step
explaining how it applies to my project
here also
thank you professor giuntani for
recommending this tutorial from
medium.com
reality can be called a collection of
hidden variables
which i'll label s meaning state
our reality is big and complicated but
the predator
and prey have a pretty simple reality we
can edit in a photo editor
every white tile is open every black
tile is an obstacle
let's call this area an x by y
matrix of ones and zeros let's add
two layers which are just zeros except
one one at the predator's position and
another one
at the praise position this reality
is a three by x by y matrix of ones and
zeros
but all this is hidden no one gets to
see
every part of reality at once except us
deities who
made this reality in a photo editor
predator
and prey only observe reality within a
few spaces
of their position let's say z spaces
so predator and prey get 3 by z
by z matrices of ones and zeros
which i'll label o meaning observation
they both use these small observations
to understand their larger reality
generating an inferred state
given some observation what's the
probability
reality is one state or another
if reality was one state or the other
what's the probability
to get this observation this is called
active inference our conceptualization
of reality
should maximize the likelihood of the
observations we're getting
maximizing the probability of our
observations
is the same as minimizing the negative
log of the probability of our
observations
also called our surprise
okay the tutorial notes that the
probability of an event
is equal to the sum of the probabilities
of that event
occurring alongside every alternative
for another event for instance uh the
probability of rolling a six on a die
is one out of six and if we rolled
another die next to it we can think of
that
one-sixth probability as divided into
sections based on the other die
so we can include all possibilities
for reality inside this expression we're
calling surprise
we also multiply by q of s divided by a
q
of s whatever q of s is
q of s divided by q of s is
one and multiplying by one is a
perfectly fine thing to do
now we're trying to minimize this
surprise
and that's hard it would be a little
easier to minimize
this thing because this q of s is
outside the logarithm
this expression is called free energy
thankfully it just so happens that free
energy
is the upper bound of surprise so
minimizing free energy
does minimize surprise approximately
the tutorial loses this minus sign by
inverting this fraction in the logarithm
then the tutorial shows another way to
represent
free energy with a notation i had never
heard of before
callback leibler divergence also called
relative entropy the kl
of two probability distributions is a
measure of difference which best
measures
zero when the probability distributions
are exactly the same
if we can manage that here then the free
energy happens to be equal to the
surprise
and we can probably get pretty close
because q
of s is an arbitrary nonsense function
we made up
we just have to nudge it closer to p of
s given o
to turn math into a metaphor we're
making our private notion of the
universe into something
similar to what our observations are
suggesting
professor jun tani might suggest our
private notion of the universe
should involve long short-term memory
networks
okay i'm going to quote directly from
the tutorial
just to make sure i'm reading it right
by minimizing free energy
the arbitrary distribution q of s gets
closer to the posterior
p of s given o and if they match
k l term becomes zero and free energy is
exactly equal to surprise so the more
we minimize free energy by wiggling
q of s the more it becomes closer to
surprise
since it's an upper bound and by
minimizing free energy
by wiggling parameters of p of s and s
we can minimize surprise even further
so that's what it means to actively
infer
for one discrete moment but because
reality changes
in every moment we can't stick to one
discrete moment
our inner model might not work so well
with whatever we observe
next so we have to improve our model in
every time step and reality can change
based on what we chose to do lately to
minimize
free energy we've got to choose our own
actions responsibly
at every time step we approximate these
terms for every possible
policy we might like to consider our
policies and
actions several steps into the future
but we can't predict
the future so we've got to approximate
it
i'm skipping a few complicated steps
here but the tutorials
final way to write free energy is like
this
the sum of cost and ambiguity
to quote the tutorial again because i
think this is the sort of thing i might
be learning to understand for
months or years the left term called
cost or risk favors policies that will
result in observations we like
and the right term ambiguity quantifies
how uncertain is the mapping between
state
and observations let's cover the
tutorials
incredibly simple example and then try
to stretch that example
out to my predator slash prey project
proposal
suppose the universe has only two
possible states
your stomach has food or your stomach
does not have food there are only two
possible observations
two feeling fed or feeling hungry
there are also only two possible actions
eating
or not eating where does a
mind fit into this squint or you'll miss
it
says the tutorial we like to be fed and
not hungry so we assign a higher
probability
to observation one fed in other words
we express preferences over observations
as probability p of o doesn't that
sound a little backward i thought we'd
be estimating probability but the
concept of
assigning probability to our
observations makes it sound the other
way around
we want to feel fed so we're putting a
higher probability
on the chance of us feeling fed
when we make a decision we consider our
high likelihood to feel fed
and that might inspire us to feed
ourselves because that would explain the
feeling fed
to put it the tutorials way we start by
estimating the hidden states under each
policy
and end up acting such as we observe
what we expect no wonder motivational
speakers are all about
optimism and vision the numbers say
you go where you aim not everyone who
thinks they become
president becomes president but no one
who thinks
they won't become president becomes
president they don't bother taking any
of the steps
so if we want our computer to do
something for us
we should tell it this is going to be
accomplished
i'm 100 sure do it
so let's stretch this out to the
predator
and pray the reality here is bigger than
two states food or no food there's a
whole
three by x by y matrix of zeros and ones
the observations are bigger than boolean
ii
the predator and prey both have a three
by z
by z matrix of zeros and ones and they
can tell how far
apart they are from the other agent pred
and
prey both have four possible actions up
left down
or right i want the predator to chase
the prey
so i tell it closeness has high
probability
when the predator makes a decision it
picks
the action which leads to what i told it
to expect at the same time
i want the prey to escape from the
predator so i tell it distance has a
high probability
when the prey makes a decision it picks
the action which leads to what i told it
to expect
this predator and prey are animated by
me
hi but i'm confident with the right
setup
fristen's free energy principle could
get these two agents
moving as if by their own thought
how no matter how much i read i don't
think i'll ever find a tutorial
which explains where the thoughts come
from
really there are no quote-unquote
thoughts here when i made those
generative adversarial networks which
produced pokemon pictures
i never wondered gosh where did that
pokemon come from
i never gave the generator a pokemon how
did it get one
the pokemon i see don't live in the
generator
or the picture the pokemon i see come
from
within me the viewer the observer
the beholder i've been reading a book
called
you are the universe by depak chopra the
book tries to disprove
a determinist notion of the mind it says
the mind isn't limited by the brain
because the brain is not the origin of
the mind
as the sort of math squid who makes this
sort of video essay
i'll always be ranting about the
complexity of machine learning
algorithms deep as the human brain
but when i perceive the predator and
pray seeming to make their own decisions
even though i know their thoughts i'm
seeing are my own
i wonder where my thoughts are coming
from
who does the thinking here at thinkster
the tutorial gets more explicit with the
math in another post
and i'll get there eventually i'll get
there eventually
because i believe it's likely that i
will get there eventually and therefore
i reliably choose actions
which lead me closer to getting there
eventually because that's what i expect
somehow there is little doubt in my mind
that this
is how the mind works i'll see you a few
time steps in the future
bye-bye by the way i've got a patreon
at patreon.com thinkster
i want to thank all these squidlings and
elder squids
thanks
[Music]